Guide to the William Hepburn Buckler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Hepburn Buckler papers
1907-1937
MS 654
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(7 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, political reports, papers relating to the Paris Peace Conference, and printed materials of William H. Buckler, diplomat and archaeologist. The bulk of the papers relate to Buckler's work as a member of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace in Paris, 1918-1919, although there is material relating to his other diplomatic duties as well as his work as an archaeologist, especially the excavations at Sardis (1910-1914) and Anatolia (1922-1930)
Buckler, W. H. (William Hepburn), 1867-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. V. H. Seymer in 1957-1958.
Biographical / Historical
William H. Buckler practiced law in Baltimore, Maryland from 1892-1905. He was Secretary to the American Legation in Madrid from 1907-1909. From 1910-1914 Buckler participated in the excavations at Sardis. He was a Special Agent at the U.S. Embassy in London from 1914-1918, and in 1919 served as a staff member of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace. Buckler was active in the field of archaeology from 1920-1930.
Scope and Contents
The Buckler collection, given to the Yale University Library by Mrs. V. H. Seymer in 1957 and 1958, comprises the personal papers of her father William Hepburn Buckler (1867-1952) - diplomat and archaeologist, son of Dr. Thomas Hepburn Buckler, and half-brother of Henry White (United States Ambassador to Italy and France, 1907-1909, and a member of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace in Paris in 1918-1919). The collection spans the period 1909-1937, with the bulk of the material falling within the years 1910-1930.
Buckler was born in Paris and spent most of his early years in England and France. As a youth he was educated by private tutors at home; subsequently he matriculated at Trinity College, Cambridge. In 1892 Buckler married Georgina Grenfell Walrond (later a distinguished Byzantine scholar), and for the next thirteen years the couple lived primarily in Baltimore, where Buckler practiced law and took a serious interest in the civic affairs of the city. In 1906, almost as a lark, Buckler passed the newly-established entrance examinations for the Foreign Service in the Department of State; and although today Buckler is chiefly remembered as an archaeologist of some note¹his earlier, diplomatic career appears to have been just as interesting.² Indeed it seems likely that, had it not been for Buckler's disillusionment with the postwar peace settlement, the Foreign Service would have remained his principal professional occupation.
Buckler first served as Secretary at the American Legation in Madrid (1907-1909). Then, after participating in the American-sponsored archaeological expeditions to Sardis (1910-1914) and doing volunteer work with the ambulance corps in France during the first months of the World War, he was appointed Special Agent at the United States Embassy in London (December 1914), where he remained posted for the duration of the conflict.
While living in London Buckler acted ostensibly as "director" of the embassy's "Austro-Hungarian division" and - later - as its resident "expert" on Balkan and Turkish affairs; but his principal role was that of a confidential reporter having direct lines of communication with Colonel E. M. House and the White House. As Buckler himself noted shortly before his death, his wartime reports from England, "transmitted to Colonel House, and by him to President Wilson, aimed at giving the views of the Liberal and Labour M. P.'s and Press which the Ambassador [W. H. Page] and the overworked Counsellor and Secretaries could not supply. Ramsay MacDonald and many others who were never seen at the Embassy were thus enabled to keep in touch with Washington. [Buckler's] ability to avoid censorship by means of the Embassy pouch gave [him] facile contact with [Colonel] House, and with [his] half-brother Henry White."
After the Armistice, and for the better part of 1919, Buckler served in various capacities as a special staff member of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace. He was thus involved in many of the debates and discussions amongst American and Allied "experts" over questions pertaining to Russia, the Balkans, and the Near East. Buckler retired from the Foreign Service in 1920 and established his permanent residence at Oxford; from that time on he devoted his energies almost exclusively to archaeological matters.
For the student of political and diplomatic history the most interesting sections of the Buckler collection are to be found in the files of the Buckler-House correspondence (Series I), covering the period August 1916-August 1918. But one should not overlook Buckler's letters written from the Paris Peace Conference, some of which were addressed to his family, others to Colonel House with whom he had continued to correspond throughout this period. With regard to the peace conference special mention must also be made of Buckler's notes on his meetings with Maxim Litvinoff at Stockholm (mid-January 1919) which laid the groundwork for the ill-fated Prinkipo conference on the Russian question.
Apart from Buckler's correspondence with House, the bulk of the collection contains letters from Buckler addressed to his wife and daughter. These have been divided into five sub-categories: (a) letters written from Madrid (1909); (b) letters written between September and November 1914, when Buckler was working as an orderly in a military hospital in France; (c) letters describing Buckler's continental tour with Samuel Gompers (1918), and mission to Stockholm (1919); (d) general correspondence of the Peace Conference period; and (e) correspondence describing in detail the excavations which took place at Sardis (1910-1914) and Anatolia (1922-1930).
¹ See the memorial notice on Buckler by W. M. Calder in The Proceedings of the British Academy, XL (1954).
² It is reviewed, all too briefly, by W. C. Dunning in his (unpublished) M. A. thesis submitted to George Washington University in 1957.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. General Correspondence. II. Miscellaneous Political Reports. III. The Peace Conference: Miscellaneous Papers. IV. Miscellaneous Printed Materials.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Archaeology; World War, 1914-1918; Europe; Middle East; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; United States -- Foreign relations -- Soviet Union; United States -- Politics and government -- 1919-1933; Archaeologists; Diplomats; Buckler, W. H. (William Hepburn), 1867-1952; Frazier, Arthur Hugh, 1868-; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938; Litvinov, M. M. (Maksim Maksimovich), 1876-1951; MacDonald, James Ramsay, 1866-1937; Page, Walter Hines, 1855-1918; Trevelyan, Charles Philips, Sir, 1870-1958; White, Henry, 1850-1927; Paris Peace Conference. United States Territorial Section ( 1919-1920. United States Territorial Section) -- 1919-1920
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, Series I
  - E. M. House
    - General
      - Buckler-House (33), 1920-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Buckler-House (8), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - London
      - House to Buckler (15), 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Buckler to House (24), 1916 July - 1917 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Buckler to House (9), 1917 March - May (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Buckler to House (20), 1917 May - August (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Buckler to House (29), 1917 August - 1919 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Buckler to House (3), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - House to Henry White [re: Buckler's London Assignment] (2), 1918 July 25, 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        General note
        See also: box 5, folders 8-13
  - Georgina G. Buckler
    - General
      - W. H. B. [Madrid] to G. G. B. (41), 1909 January - March (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - W. H. B. [Madrid] to G. G. B. (30), 1909 March - April (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - W. H. B. [Madrid] to G. G. B. (19), 1909 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - W. H. B. [Madrid] to G. G. B. (65), 1909 May - June (Box 1, Folder 12A)
      - W. H. B. [France] to G. G. B. (30), 1914 September 4-16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - W. H. B. [France] to G. G. B. (10), 1914 September 18 - October 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - W. H. B. [France] to G. G. B. (15), 1914 October 2 - November 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - W. H. B. [London] to G. G. B. (3), 1914 December - 1915 January (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - W. H. B. [London] to G. G. B. (10), 1916 December (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - W. H. B. to G. G. B. [Gompers trip] (11), 1918 September - October (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - W. H. B. to G. G. B. [Stockholm Mission] (11), 1919 January - February (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - W. H. B. [Paris] to G. G. B. (22), 1919 March 11 - April 26 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - W. H. B. [Paris] to G. G. B. (18), 1919 March 5 - June 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - W. H. B. [Paris] to G. G. B. (26), 1919 June 11 - September 5 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - W. H. B. [Paris] to G. G. B. (28), 1919 September 6 - October 9 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - W. H. B. [Paris] to G. G. B. (23), 1919 October 28 - December 6 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - W. H. B. [London, Holland, Germany] to G. G. B. (7), 1919 September 2-12 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - W. H. B. [United States] to G. G. B. (10), 1920 September 26 - November 5 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - W. H. B. [Berlin] to G. G. B. (6), 1927 May 23-27 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Archaeological
      - [W. H. B. to G. G. B.] [List of lacunae in correspondence from archaeological expeditions, 1911-1930] (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - W. H. B. [Constantinople] to G. G. B. (4), 1907 August (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (18), 1910 May 5-26 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (14), 1910 May 30 - June 21 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (21), 1911 January 27 - March 1 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (15), 1911 March 2 - April 13 (Box 2, Folder 32A)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (18), 1911 April 10 - June 6 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (15), 1912 February 15 - May 12 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (12), 1912 May 14 - June 19 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (17), 1913 February 4 - March 25 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (10), 1913 March 27 - April 30 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (16), 1913 May 1 - June 28 (Box 3, Folder 37A)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (20), 1914 April 5 - 28 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to G. G. B. (17), 1914 April 30 - June 27 (Box 3, Folder 38A)
      - W. H. B. [Constantinople] to G. G. B. (3), 1922 June 12 - 17 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - W. H. B. [Near East] to G. G. B. (13), 1924 May 28 - June 29 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - W. H. B. [Anatolia] to G. G. B. (16), 1926 April 26 - June 30 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - W. H. B. [Geneva] to G. G. B. (2), 1926 March - June (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - W. H. B. [Anatolia] to G. G. B. (9), 1929 April 10 - May 22 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - W. H. B. [Anatolia] to G. G. B. (16), 1930 March 28 - June 7 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - W. H. B. [Europe and Cyprus] to G.G. B. (19), 1932 January - Sep, 1934 March - April (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Others
    - Lucy Buckler
      - W. H. B. [Sardis] to L. B. (44), 1910 May 10 - 1914 June 10 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - W. H. B. [Paris] to L. B. (including one letter from H. White to L. B., 1919 March 5) (7), 1919 September 14 - November 4 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - C. O. de Dardel
      - W. H. B. and C. O. de Dardel (3), 1918 February 15-25 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Arthur Hugh Frazier
      - W. H. B. to A. H. F. (10), 1918 December 5-27 (Box 4, Folder 48A)
    - Walter Hines Page
      - W. H. B. to W. H. P. (3), 1918 May - December (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Charles Trevelyan
      - W. H. B. and C. T. (7), 1916 October - 1917 May (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Henry White
      - W. H. B. to H. W. (5), 1918 March - July (Box 4, Folder 51)
- MISCELLANEOUS POLITICAL REPORTS, Series II
  - British Political Personalities
    - E. D. Morel [Union of Democratic Control] to Buckler, 1917 February 15 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Ramsay MacDonald to Buckler, 1917 June - August (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - H. Grenfell to Buckler, 1918 March (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Memoranda
    - Memorandum by Buckler for W. H. Page re: information on Bulgaria from Major Newbold, 1917 June 20 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum by Buckler of interview with Sidney Webb, 1918 March 10 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Memorandum by Buckler of conversation with Member of British Shipping Interests, 1918 December 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Memorandum by Buckler on conversations with A. Henderson and G. Fitzmaurice, 1918 December 18 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Draft Program Decisive Settlement Committee,", 1917 (Box 5, Folder 7A)
  - Reports to Colonel House
    - Reports: Buckler to Colonel House, 1917 December 10 - 1918 June 29 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Reports: Buckler to Colonel House, 1916 September 30 - 1917 June 14; 1917 June 21 - December 31; 1918 January 10 - May 4; 1918 May 9 - mid-December (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
    - Index of Persons in Buckler-House Reports (Box 5, Folder 13)
- PEACE CONFERENCE, MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS, Series III
  - General
    - Memorandum of a conversation between Buckler and M. Cachin, 1919 March 28 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Peace Mission, Paris, from Garrett Droppers, American Legation, Athens, 1919 March 31 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - notes on the Meeting of the Commissioners and the Technical Experts of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace, Paris, 1919 July 8 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Telegram to the Secretary of State, Washington, from Paris re: Meeting of the Council of the Heads of Delegations on 1919 August 7, 1919 August 9 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - notes of a Meeting of the Heads of Delegations of the Five Great Powers Held in M. Pinchon's Room, Quai D'Orsay, Paris, Wednesday, 1919 November 12, at 10:30 A. M. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Copy of a letter from W. M. Ramsay to Buckler, 1919 February 11, re: treaty settlements regarding Greeks in Anatolia (Forwarded by Buckler to C. Day, 1919 February 12) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Report of the American Section of The International Commission on Mandates in Turkey, submitted by the Commissioners Charles R. Crane and Henry Churchill King, Paris, 1919 August 28 (Box 6, Folder 6A)
    - Memorandum on the policy of the United States relative to the Treaty with Turkey, by Buckler, 1919 November 26 (Box 6, Folder 6B)
  - Russia
    - Copy of letter by Maxim Litvinov to Dr. L. Meyer, Christiania (Sweden), stating Soviet's possible position, 1919 January 10 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - notes: Meetings of Maxim Litvinov and Buckler, Stockholm, 1919 January 14, 15, 16 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - notes of the views of Arthur Ransome on Russia and the Peace Conference, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- MISCELLANEOUS PRINTED MATERIALS, Series IV
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Clippings: "Les Derniers Nouvelles," Aix-Les Bains, 1914 August 5-18 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Clippings: Manchester Guardian The Times, London, 1918 January 9, undated, 1918 February 12 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Clippings: Italian Newspapers [Gompers Mission], 1918 October 14, 17, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Printed Miscellanea
    - Printed poster re: Conscription, Douai, France, 1918 February 10 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - List of Countries Whose Interests or Archives in Other Countries are in Charge of American Diplomatic and Consular Officers, 1916 February 14 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Reports of Visits of Inspection Made by Officials of the United States Embassy to Various Internment Camps in the United Kingdom. London, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - note from the United States Ambassador transmitting a Report, dated June 5, 1915, on the conditions at present existing in the Internment Camp at Ruhleben. London, 1915 June 8 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with the United States Ambassador respecting the Treatment of British Prisoners of War and Interned Civilians in Germany. London, 1915 June (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Report of the Interallied Commission of Inquiry on the Greek Occupation of Smyrna and Adjacent Territories, 1919 Oct, November (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Treaty of Peace with Turkey, Sevres, August 10, 1920; Tripartite Agreement between the British Empire, France and Italy respecting Anatolia, Sevres, 1920 August 10 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Proceedings, Reports and Documents of the Interallied Commission of the Left Bank of the Rhine, 1919 May 29 - June 9, June 13 - July 29 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Agreement between the United States of America, Belgium, the British Empire and France and Germany with regard to the military occupation of the territories of the Rhine (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Thesis on William H. Buckler
    - "The Diplomatic Career of William Hepburn Buckler," by W. C. Dunning. Master's Essay, George Washington University, 1957 February 22 (Box 7, Folder 12)